[Music]
okay so I'm here with my old friend
Fabrice middle he's the founder of the
Ecole oxidant abdullah meditation which
is a meditation school in paris a very
big meditation school which is really I
think it's quite an original and and
revolutionary kind of school and
different than a lot of other schools of
this sort and Fabrice is also a author
of many many books including the French
art of not giving a fuck which I haven't
read yet but I've read many many of your
books and I've been following your work
over the years and I wanted to talk to
you because I want to introduce you to
some of my friends and in the English
world because because I think of what
you do is very important so maybe I
could you just start by like introducing
yourself a little bit say what what your
what your school is about what your
mission is about and and what is this
French art of not giving a fuck so maybe
I discover meditation when I was 21 I
was studying philosophy and I had the
chance to be at one of the one of my
teacher was Francisco Varela was an
important neuroscientist who try to
understand meditation as a way to
understand the mind and he was he was
the man who really created all ID of man
and life Institute with the Dalai Lama
and so I was introduced into meditation
by him in a very um
solid and profound way he was a very in
love with meditation and after through
em I I get into Tibetan Buddhism to
understand meditation and study with
different teacher and 15 years ago 17
years ago I thought that we need to talk
to to give transmission of meditation
not only inside of Buddhist but more
broad way more broad and yes and you
consider your school to be like secular
rather than religious or is that a bad
way of putting it I wasn't the problem i
RI i ad but i found that it's difficult
to really see it from outside but
seventeen years ago there was very few
meditation in many buddhist center some
people think that you have meditation
inside of the religious and when you put
it outside you meet it you make
meditation lighter more sample for
people who don't have the courage to
engage into buddhism that was not at all
my experience i was very i I saw that
there was few and we took a lot about
that with Francisco was very
disappointed himself by the fact that in
Buddhist people get into a religious
idea of devotion and and believing guru
and many things that didn't allow them
to go already into the profanity of
meditation yeah perhaps we can say the
opposite is true that it's much much
harder to practice meditation
in the middle of Paris or in your busy
life and I will not say is yeah I will
say but for me the decision was to try
to be faithful to the artisans of
meditations that I found that was the
words of problem and that was one of
things I I was I thought we have to go
into present in meditation in a larger
way but also the situation came because
I saw that there was a particle into
schools that I knew of Tibetan Buddhism
in also school a lot of corruption I was
a very I was in great pain to see a so
much correction power manipulation of
sex and money not say not telling the
truth gift fight of power and i found i
i something was not true and it was a
time of great great pain for me so at
this time i'd ready to open meditation
in a large way to go into - so with i
still presenting and we still studying
buddhist but not in a religious way but
we go back to the text we'll go back to
tibetan chinese sanskrit and we we
question the text we try to be more like
we call in waste paramagnetic we try to
have to not take the text as something
fixed but more some things that ask to
be a read and interpret in relation to
all the text or the knowledge yeah and I
forgot to mention
Fabrice that you're a philosopher as
well and you studied a lot of philosophy
and perhaps that informs your Western
philosophy and perhaps that I'm sure
that informs how how you look at
Buddhist texts and and reinterpret them
yes because either as Westerners feel if
Western philosophy very intensively I
did a PhD in La Sorbonne but more in a
more deep way I found that that is very
strange
when you are Westerners to go into by
example Buddhist and just forget about
knowledge of the West one - I was very I
was more and more struck by the fact
that erm many people talk about Buddhist
but in fact when you know Western
philosophy you realized they just talk
about Western philosophy without knowing
it by many people think they talk about
Buddhists so just talking about a candle
first choice young Stacie's right and
Epicure I don't occur in ISM yeah I
remember you saying that before that a
lot of the Buddhism in the West is a
kind of epicureanism and stoicism yes
using Buddhist sort of terminology but
but yes but they haven't really got to
the depth of the truth by example
everybody took that put the Buddhist now
is a impermanence you say that interment
permanencia so that for that is almost
the basic level that everybody agree but
honestly is so simple to believe the
idea of impermanence is is not so
general in making particle Buddhists and
and commoners is a definition of the
nature of reality you make a statement
about reality to be impermanence that
not at all the point of view of Buddhist
would never is a metaphysic we try to
say what is reality
Buddhism is more kind of practice and
the knowledge of Buddhists is more way
to help you to see more clearly you own
relation to reality right they not have
this kind of object
mmm can I just try to understand
Buddhist or do you mean it's like the
idea of impermanence or something like
that is is not some kind of description
of reality it's it's one sort of thing
to work with one kind of it's a process
of trying to understand yes so yes and
is a process is the way to shunt you
mind but we make Buddhist like a
description of reality which is very
weak so so and you have all these people
who say ah yes the athlete said we never
go to time in the same river and that is
like Buddha and we make this link which
is extremely weak because if a kid was
not saying at all that was much much
more deeper and we make things so weak
and we try and we think we know about
Buddhist we just projecting on Buddhist
distort view that we can have a kind of
objective grasp on reality and truth
Allah knows have a better grasp on
reality which is easy and many many
things like that and so isn't we're not
going into detail but it will be
venturing to see that why many people
observe I did that on Buddhist is just
wishes is also all idea of a taxi so
that mean you are you are calm down you
are relaxed which has nothing to do with
Buddhist yeah no this is actually like
during the covert crisis that a lot of
people are doing meditation courses
online and it's always about calming
down and and dealing with stress and
dealing with your troubles like this and
and I think what you're trying to say is
that there's an adventure to meditation
and and a rigor and that it's not it's
not some kind of
you know tranquilizer that you take to
to calm your mind
yes so the first point was Buddhism in
the West unfortunately over the year and
become more I've lost the the life that
was in Buddhist when they come in the
West in the 1780s groans later on first
you have generation of people who was in
retreat in Tibet for 20 years 30 years
who came to the West there was something
so deep so real in them that it touch
people but the new generation people get
more interested in power and
manipulation and I thought we need to
open meditation to everyone that was the
first step the second step happened ten
years ago seven years ago I realize that
meditation I I realized that I was
facing a new problem
meditation become like we just talked
before a way to tronky lies yourself to
just can down to just have a better to
just to manage stress right and it
stressed the and I thought that is it a
big problem because that is just manage
stress is just the whole idea of
neoliberalism you try to make people
work under the die yeah manage
everything - yeah right manager manage
everything love life your your your
stress your you know it's a kind of
control and and then meditation just
becomes another one of those yes those
things another product yes yeah and one
thing is is not effective it doesn't
work no you say to people manage your
stress worst they are because nobody can
do it more you say manage your stress
worse you are because you everyone is a
stress everybody at anxiety pen and that
is part of human life
and the idea of managing you should
manage you bank account but you can't
manage your own heart your own living
and the fact that we using economic
image about everything just is part of
the problem
so when medication is there for managing
you stress is just creating more problem
that help and I found that was a big
problem there was a big problem because
I saw that people trying to doing that
by doing that they were losing their own
aunt they feel guilty because I never
succeed they feel guilty to feel pain
fear anxiety they feel like is something
is wrong with them they and they want
from meditation become someone someone
else and the ol ID to loosen meditation
as you have to calm down
I find that is extremely aggressive and
that I was my that was my very I was
very strike by that because when I saw
Fe any sorry I was going to say that a
meditation retreat for example you you
experience all kinds of pain and
suffering and it's hard and challenging
and yes it makes it you know it's
nothing really if you go to a Zen you
know machine for example this has
nothing to do with being calm it's no
really it's it's it's about getting to
the nature of reality you're getting to
the depths of things yes so I find that
the old approach of meditation to get to
manage your stress just avoid people to
do what meditation is about contacting
you on aren't you own pain transforming
making more in peace and I really make a
distinction between calm and peace when
the
when the sea is gone the boat can't move
peace you can be in peace and letting
pen we can be in peace and be anxious
about the future of our world that the
idea of can is like you enter into your
own little bubble pink bubble or purple
bubble and you are in your own little
things and you are in peace and you have
come to our country and I find that is a
big forum so that was for me a big
difficulties I was teaching meditation
and ER and I realized that people don't
get it people I was giving a seminar and
I remember and people were having the
feelings I don't succeed to doing it
they all of the cleaning I can't arrive
to do meditation and I realized that the
aura trusts that by doing meditation you
should being calm
you should have no soul you should and
they have make a list of things for them
what meditation should be and they'd
feel guilty that they don't arrive to go
into this approach and I realized that
we have to find another way and in in
front is where I start to say foot evila
pay and unfortunately is very difficult
to translate into English no no I think
that's a wonderful translation the
French art of not giving a fuck it just
it's maybe it's too pop babies to poppy
but even it has knowledge as good as
suitable appear because footage will I
pay first there is the work piece yeah
and food EVOO is really a is really a
give yourself peace by just stop
torturing yourself I see and so I make I
start to talk about about the I try to
start to talk to meditation truth is
that for
and there was two choosing by doing that
one thing is we become I try to cut the
neoliberalism that is destroying our
human relation to ourselves to others to
nature through the earth and but I also
in this way try to go back into an odd
deep relation to meditation that you
have in Tibetan Buddhists in ma mudra or
suction by the fact that you you you
completely relax into the true nature of
reality you you just you use you stop to
try to improve yourself but you have a
glimpse of space of open space but that
you could find in other spiritual
religious you have that in hazardous
movement in Judaism you have that in in
in Christianity I was very interesting
in all the types of the seven French
17th centuries of Christian texts
because they say it was there was a time
of flourishing kind of meditation and
you are just given in and just relaxing
to the the secure nature of love that is
in yourself so many interesting so I
find that without having to go into this
text in detail that are that make people
are sometimes afraid of this approach
because there is bad there is I I am by
this approach of not giving a fuck you
go back to something more deep into the
level of meditation and the book had a
very strong impact in France it was one
of the book who sells the most so yeah I
could be shit five or six years ago I
was in saloons a year so tonight you can
I tell you tell you why the title speaks
to me because well I'm an English person
living in France and there's something
about anglo-saxon mentality that gets
very hyper sight psychological about
everything and there's also this as you
say this kind of marketing approach to
life so when I so so one of the things I
love about being here is something about
the French spirit that that that has
that that quality of not giving a fuck
if that makes any sense yes yeah yes so
so was the book had a very strong impact
and because people are suffering a lot
by this approach of having to manage
themselves you know you found in many in
many place people are doing burn out the
over stress and the only message of that
is your food you should manage yourself
better and I try to to show that is not
true is people are they just suffer from
a very ant approach of a flaw is trying
them from and very hard and and
themselves now who's the out of themself
they don't like that people don't like
themselves because they are integrate
this politically social vision that we
never do enough could say the mantra of
our time is you don't you don't
enough are you you little now you listen
to me
but have you done enough no no and that
create a doubt no yes that's true and
you should do more and being means doing
more being more efficient and this that
is like is very person that truly
destroy yourself and I find is important
because we can't there is a tendency
that when we talk about meditation
spirituality and so on we have a
tendency to think that everything is in
your own mind but that is really weak
because there is also violence in our
times and it's very important to be able
to name it to name what is the problem
of our time the violence of our area and
I must say that my great inspiration in
all that was Shogun Trungpa Rinpoche
really is in really is very great source
of influence and because comparing
Persia was passing the only Tibetan
Buddhist teacher who really try to
understand the singularity of our time
and where he was talking in many
different way but one way was he said we
live in the times of what he called the
Setting Sun mortality that is opposed to
the Great Eastern Sun metallic and it is
we have some link with nature because
this whole idea that we we prefer going
to sleep that this the morning when you
have to wake up and to and to say yes to
the difficulty of life and the settings
are not adequate for him was destroying
earth by just trying to meet more
comfortable and the way to willing to be
more confortable for him was really like
a present while destroying and is what
he calls the Setting Sun mortality who
said is immortal
she offer in a niche where you could say
Neely's nihilism here here you could say
also is a mentality of trying to go to
find comfort in every situation and try
meditation was not trying to find
comfort but to to to to be more right
away to be more treasures to be more to
be more sharp about what what is really
key and for me even if I don't
necessarily use the same word I found
that a great inspiration that we have to
think historically what creates the
particle time to understand more in
which way meditation could be relevant
to our time when you think about the
Buddha the first thing that one of the
first thing that the Buddha did when he
start to teach meditation we start to
have a very strong analyze of the
society where he was living in we start
to say all strike on the whole structure
of our society is wrong because the
whole idea of of caste system yes it's
wrong and separation between man and
woman and woman can have known no
possibility to go into the spiritual
world is wrong so it's very strong that
we make now an image of Buddha of some
say of someone with pure and livid read
the world and when you see his life he
was very engaged in to analyzing what
prevent life to flourish and I think
what prevent life to flourish today that
from the point of view of meditation I
think that the key point and what
prevent life is his idea that we have to
be a tool to manage everything to be can
to me and all that is based on kind of
heartridge toward life
all this teacher of meditation now all
this application of meditation they just
based on kind of hatred toward life yeah
the contrary of Ettrick toward logic
yeah and and and if if we're talking
about Chuck Chuck I'm shrimper and I
also extremely inspired by him I think I
think that for me he was the most
authentic teacher you know in in the
West and and his and and his example
what was always the most a live
situation right yes not not not some
kind of you know escape from from from
reality yes he was yes he was able to go
into the negativity of the world to try
to transmute the negativity and he was
not the kind of this kind of naive light
love
yeah well cooking which is so poorness
and and he was a tantric teacher and it
seems like today a tantric teacher is
something that he can't be a public
thing because it's too alive and because
we want to make everything a product and
we want to define everything and we want
to make everything safe and and pure and
and and you know I'm good and dead
exactly yeah yes there is a lack of love
there's a lack of you could say a very
key point is we are destroying all the
link between meditation and love hmm
and I think there is many Krampus as
many different side one side is Howie it
was into understanding history the
historical circularity of our time and
of particle Neil ISM from our times
every I have every time I've his own
close way to be close autumn is not
worse than any other times but every
time of it every time I have a different
way to be close
mm-hmm in other times religion become
with Inquisition you said this before
you said every time has its denial of
love I think I think that's what you
said I remember you saying and and and
our denial of love is how would you how
would you characterize that good if you
look if you go back in some centuries so
close the way that the time is close by
example by religious hatred hmm you have
to belong to one religion otherwise we
have to kill yourself you were killed
there was better between religions there
was Inquisition Inquisition who God who
burned witches who burn wood burn people
who think differently but our time is
closed by this way of willing everybody
to be happy happy in very now now now no
way like just every you have to have
your own capital capital you say capital
can oh yeah you have your capital hence
you capital a penis you capital and you
are very resources another is a word you
could use as the capital is better
because is it sure that your own
relation to yourself is like a relation
to capital and people even people who
talk about the disaster of a kind of
capitalism you don't respect anything
don't respect your people don't respect
people in a poor country don't respect
nature don't respect don't see that we
have integrated the same way of looking
our selves
doing the same thing and is really lack
of flow of love lack of being able to to
be open to reality as it is duality to
be more to flourish to be more current
hmm you have you have a provocative book
called becoming narcissistic as it is
that the name of the book I wanted to
bring that up because I also thought
that because almost everybody
one of the biggest insults you could
call somebody today and it's it's the
diagnosis of the culture right is that
everybody is becoming narcissistic and
you're you're you're reinterpreting the
myth of narcissists and I think this is
beautiful as some as something else so I
maybe you could yes so first I will say
I'm not reinterpreting the meet I'm just
telling what the meet is about because
just ah just to be sure
nothis not seasick is the name of a
flower you have the same flower in in
English Nasus yeah I think so yeah so
now this is the name of a flower it's
the name of the first flower of spring
in spring you have but thousand of
nasa's who is the first flower is the
flower sometime is white with the front
yellow sometime is only yellow and you
have different can't and um was
wondering why there will be a meet of a
man who is so full of himself
so a goose on trick so full of ego that
in the name by the name of a flower in
make no sense so i try to go back to the
meet and try to understand and i
realized that the meat is not about beef
completely full of yourself but just be
in contact with yourself and recognizing
yourself and all historical stories of
the Metis Nasus
didn't recognize himself in the water
didn't know who he was and he was lost
he well he didn't was able to love other
people he didn't know how to love
himself he was cut from his family it
was in pain and true recognizing his
true nature to recognizing we was he
becomes like the flower like the Eagle
no flash that what the meat so when he
falls into the water he falls into the
to everything or some person dead yes
and and his why the book is why the book
is one of the one of one place when you
find histories is metamorphosis
metamorphosis because it becomes a
metamorphose into the flower but at one
point one point the second point is
everybody tried to say that we live a
time when people are very nice is it
and I found we live in a time when
people are very very hard times to just
become who they are there are so into
oppression I was just starting to stew
truth to realize that with repeating
something and I just see the contrary I
don't see around me people who are full
of themselves I found a lot of people
who don't arrive to sing by themselves
to feel what they feel to be in contact
with their own art and I find it's very
strong that we what we're saying is
exactly the contrary we live in a time
when people are don't have space don't
have time
don't have resources to be in contact
with with the profundity of their own
life so I find no we're not in a time of
NASA seek we have a time when people
have really deeply cut from the own
inner life and and that was really from
that's that the hatred you are talking
about we don't arrive to like our true
to be a deep love relation to ourselves
because we are catch
- the 12:04 life so some people said to
me but no you can't say that people like
Trump are completely not seasick and I
said no Trump is not nasty sick trap
don't like himself because if he was
really in if he was really having a deep
perform loving relation to himself it
will be not denying reality and tried it
to prove the always that is right when
you are in love with yourself you don't
have to make so much effort that
convince you don't have to put your
picture on Instagram every every five
minutes to convince everybody how
beautiful you are
is that because because this is exactly
the opposite of nasty seek is a fuller
are you say of gay in English or pride
pride fight and when and pride what is
pride pride is willing to be someone you
are not you be so afraid of who you are
you have to create an image of what you
want to be I find it's very strange that
we we mixed loving yourself by the fact
that being pride of creating an image
because you don't love yourself I just
saw that is very basic psychology and
and our fad meditation is a way to
meditation is a way to be able to
recognize something a gift that is in
yourself a gold that is in your own art
and that is not seasick and philosophy
is a bird you can sing by yourself you
could say what the beginning of
philosophy in the West with Socrates is
so quite arrived everywhere talked to
people and said what you think what you
think is important even if you are
nobody I don't care what do you think
you that is what philosophy was in the
West and that is not see see because
everybody has the ability to sing by
themselves so I was trying to - yes to
sink and those are
of meditation that is very I find
meditation the approve of meditation is
so weak so naive so full of he's very
weak there's no new trust no love no
vision but is really that was but bother
me at the end of the like the beginning
of the century there were all of these
kind of schools there were all these
kind of schools in Sweden and in
Northern Europe that sprung up and they
were kind of you know schools where you
would train you would train in
philosophy you would train in meditation
you had trained and all these different
kinds of things rather than just doing
one thing and I think I think you're
kind of doing the same thing your school
is very you have a lot of ask there's a
lot of elements to it there's a lot of
different things so that meditation
doesn't become just this little
technique that you do to relax in the
morning there's there's a whole holistic
I don't know if that's the right word
but process of learning going on right
yes so maybe you first thing if I can
correct what you said the the School of
Medicine it's not just in Paris where in
every place excuse me yeah
monkeybone world because I in morale
where in quick sale we are in Geneva we
are many other places in Switzerland and
in many places in France so we are
francophone organization and we do sing
in residential we do sing also by
internet we have class many differences
so it's true that meditation my
conviction is meditation can be like the
the forces will open to everything for
new Renaissance like the Renaissance
they they found back some Greek
inspiration through to yeah new approach
to everything I find meditation is a key
to oppose to have another approach to
politics to economics to philosophy to
art why psychology to the whole
everything my because your time is in
our time we are cut from experience
going to concept like we do this
interview in the middle of the Kovach
crisis and here confine in our own and
everybody realize how difficult is just
to know what we feel to be in contact
with what we experiment we are even if
we are at home all day long is very
difficult to cut from information that
don't tell us very much and to go into a
deeper feeling that gave us strength and
be a way to to to true I remember the
word I was looking for bill done it was
called bill dung it was a German word
and it was something about becoming a
person do you know what I'm talking
about this yes and so true medication
that concludes our relation we have with
art because odd is not just something we
have to understand something a few
people but is an experience so by
example one thing I do often is I do
meditation in middle of concert I did
that in Opera Bastille in the Great Oak
Island at best the last October someone
play music I do a negatives of
meditation she plays the same piece and
we ask people what they expense and then
and there are completely surprised and
shocked yeah was buying doing five
minutes of meditation the ear music like
they never
earned because in our times people don't
get trained to to listen to to listen to
feel to feel and we are very into
concept very abstract and very difficult
for us to learn what means the senses
Sensibility you know when you go to at
school from all years never you have
class when you learn how to go into the
Google Oh to go deeper into what means
feeling so meditation so we do we do
many thing about art in our school of
meditation yeah and that's what I wanted
I mean that's what I think is so unique
about yes which in venture school we can
go to me and make meditation with
panting to have another relation to
panting we could ask that with music and
we could have that so we have class
sometimes with many different thing we
had a class on Beethoven lately and we
were trying to to go deeper into into
Beethoven I must say that in philosophy
I was very much marked by film energy I
found that there was a lot of link
between phenomenology and meditation
phenomenology was this idea that start
at the beginning of the 20th centuries -
maybe not good not make philosophy a way
to elaborate concept but more into
describing experience describing the
relation you have to phenomena so what
do you see what do you feel when you
listen music when you meet someone when
you have a thought when you have
imagination going to more into
describing and there is a lot of link
between meditation and phenomenology so
that was that was is one of the key and
the other thing you teaches is poetry -
right I know that you've you've taught
me a few things about about modern
poetry and and why do you think that's
that's so important and why is it so
absent from you know I think that's
that's another reason why I think what
you're doing is so
Gordon is I think that people people
have this sort of very anti poetic
spirit today it's I could torture is so
important our relation to poetry to
music to out is cultural aesthetic first
is culture that means you have to have
character I have no interest in to
character I'm not reading poetry to have
character i wit poetry to go into a
deeper relation to my own life and to
the world
and I don't know any great poet who
write poetry as a fact of character my
appropriate since the since the oldest
time is a relation to to truth the
poetry came in the West the me to
understand poetry we have to go back
into the mythology as a way to
describing what is poetry and in and the
meat of poetry is office office and
office go which is the first plate then
the mythology of the Greek mythology
said office is the first plate office go
into I will say unfair listen fail and
to hell into the underworld inside the
world into Hades or by love because I
read is the woman in love was killed by
a snake who look after her and go into
the underworld and that is all the idea
of a tree true by love you go on on the
underworld to bring back light we will
be a true light not the light of
avoiding reality but the light that go
through touching reality that is poetry
for the West for the West I always been
sought as a way to go into the
the pen and the difficulty to bring back
light yeah you see the West is that like
I guess that's different from let's say
haiku poems or or poems of the east or
is it the same thing or is it like a
universal thing or is it just oh I see
the West you don't I think that that
partically I always call it poetry and I
find that very interesting for for us
that way tree because what I want to try
to show is a lot of people are using to
poetry painting because they think is
cultural and they are intimidated
intimidated intermediate intimidated
because it's supposed to be high culture
of some kind fred is not for them and it
won't see that artists are exactly like
them the cultural world is not like them
mm-hmm because it's tried to make it
special poor are not like them but the
artists are exactly like them the people
who live in the middle of the world and
trying to bring back some light some
kind of love like everybody so that's
the first problem and the second problem
are is in relation to true aesthetic and
if the tea means I feel something
pleasant but art is not to do with
aesthetic I don't go to listen music to
feeling I feel something so good that a
missile no art is about truth is not
about just adding some kind of pleasure
it's about some candles you feel when
you when you maybe as what would you say
meaning it has its meaningful meaningful
when you listen just beyond the beyond
just just pleasure or yes or experience
when I listen Beethoven wait what I did
lately
I know just I think some nice experience
I found his music
shamea and also open my eyes to another
dimension of reality that I lost is like
the world
more real yeah and so when you
understand that your relation to the
world chant in a very deep way
yeah what are the things I've heard you
say is like searching for happiness is a
really stupid
another stupid idea of our culture or
this this search for happiness and we I
would we have to make careful about what
we call a peanut because again wonderful
work is the art of the teaching of our
histories but happiness if he becomes
just kind of comfort yeah
and of how you could that be Annette
yeah Beatriz it's a very French phrase
yeah well being well being is being yeah
there is a big distinction between
well-being and real happiness happiness
is not just well-being happiness if a
penis is because in Aristotle's
happiness the question of happiness is a
question of in which way I accomplish my
life mmm-hmm deepest and more profound
sons yeah I asking me what makes me
happy
I ask the most ethical question for my
life but having an idea that happiness
is just well-being and I don't want to
be in contact with pain suffering
anxiety is that just make me more and
more weak so there's a more profound
kind of happiness which includes you
know all of the Vista toots of life you
know pleasure pain everything you know
so one of the questions I had for you is
you know there's there seems to be
something wrong right these days with
with with Western Buddhism and just it
just seems all wrong to me it seems like
most of it is is is all wrong I don't
want to insult anybody or
or for a lot of the reasons that you're
saying so to the point where you know
what is the what is the important of
Buddhism in the West right I mean why is
Buddhism important I don't know I don't
know if he's important anymore you know
what I discover in Buddhist so that was
very profound when I was 13 years ago I
don't know if people have cannot this
contact now I don't know either
maybe they do some places but but but at
the same time you know is it's true for
everything now we have a relation with
Buddhism are we have ration with
Christianity are we have religion with
three days are we have relation to
poetry are we have relation to music how
we have relation to earth is a big
question for everyone so the question is
just how do you have a relation basic
yet how do you have a relation which is
more honest which is not based on fear
and Buddhist is wonderful Christianity
ad extraordinary profound resources way
yeah rich richness the toy tree the same
thing you know music the same thing but
sometimes I go to see I go to lesson
music and go to a concert and I see that
for many people is just a distraction
they don't go to leave the same
expounded I try to to live there and
this part of life you know yeah well
maybe listening to to Beethoven or
something like that your experience of
that has more meaning is more meaningful
in a Buddhistic sense then you know
saying a bunch of mantras and and
wearing some some some Tibetan clothing
and and and and costumes and trying to
adopt
a mentality yeah it's very interesting
that was the idea of Trump and Pacino
when he tried to talk about the whole
idea of why on sheep he tried to create
and I know the context and that would be
broader than just Buddhist yeah that was
he had this vision but I I love that I
just I love I just find Buddhism at a
very it's a very profound extraordinary
tradition and I'm still doing some
practice that come from the Tibetan
tradition
I still studying take some time some
very difficult texts and with great joy
I just found that the transmission of
Buddhism become really weak because
there is a lack of deaths and the death
is also off to go through questioning
the text having a relation to Western
philosophy cannot using word that you
know a lot of the Buddhist texts use it
kind of terminology that really is not
appropriate I just talked about
impairment but I could talk about coos
they use the word cause but cause in
Western world have nothing to do with
cause in in so often it's a question of
translation it's not very interesting to
also look at look at you know I find
myself I find myself reading meister
eckhart and things like this because
because a lot of the the stuff is just
doesn't touch me because it's it's to
Tibetan or it's it's to foreign so I
find myself one I need to study my own
culture
yes but that makes that makes the
Buddhist practice you know that we both
engage in you know more alive right if
we're studying
yeah because problem is not that Tibetan
is frame the problem is the way we
translate Tibetan Buddhist make it dead
yeah and the translation is it is not
just is more deep question that we
thought
you could say that the way the roman
translate Greek philosophy I've created
the old Roman approach in the
Renaissance the West translate in Greek
create another culture and the way in
the 19th centuries we try to translate a
new way create a new culture and you
could say in the 20th century's some
philosopher try to like Kierkegaard
nitch Heidegger try to go back to the
Greek and make a new translation create
a new approach so so that's what you're
doing that's what your mission is in a
way it's translation yeah translation is
not just translation is it's not that
you that you put your text put on google
translation and having an oscillation is
how you are how you read things you know
when people have decided that meditation
will be called mindfulness but with
translations that create a lot of
decision it's a very deep decision and
maybe that was a great mistake to call
meditation - oh yeah I talked about that
yeah talk about that that's interesting
yeah why mindfulness is just mind and
maybe meditation is not about so much
about mind maybe meditation is about
body hmm fashion is about heart maybe
make dashing should have be called
heartfulness because maybe the word
originally was mind heart or something
like that you know in tibetan or maybe
in tibet meditation meditation have
nothing to do with mindfulness
meditation is is very different
amelioration or something like that is a
word that people use sometimes being
familiar with your being interested
yourself yes
so mindfulness is not is not bad but
it's just by doing this translation you
have create an understanding of
meditation that you could question
awareness could have been another
approach which personally I found more
more profound awareness is more profound
then mindfulness or awareness I I know
how you pronounce it
he W II have so much resonance and is
the word that you find in American
poetry and and awareness is I found i'm
a found that is amazing
they're all the resonance of awareness I
will would have been very interesting to
call meditation awareness awareness
practice it will be completely different
to mindfulness practice awareness
practice yeah and so you that is just
one example we could take counted but
you just see that by doing a choice of
one translation you have an
interpretation that could really close
something yeah well it seems like also
the the history of Buddhism in the West
is very young so certain terms certain
ideas stick in another other ones oh you
know don't and no I think I will say the
problem is not that is so much so few
time because I think we were much more
open twenty or thirty years ago so
quantities we translating Buddhist and
meditation to put it in the box of the
whole idea of management and there is
mindfulness come more fit more into the
box of Management at awareness because
you you can't go to business world and
say to people you have to work more and
do some mindfulness to be more efficient
you can't say to people you do
heartfulness awareness to be more
efficient so it will not work so so this
is a term that can be easily manipulated
right is where he was promoted and and
and by translating this way we make we
our own people understand and some
people and but at some time we lose
something will
something of the of the extraordinary
power of the situation have you been
thinking about how the world is going to
be different after this pandemic and
what what's happening now and you know
what's going on much for or or is it is
it almost not too early to talk about
that sort of thing I know I think yes I
think is I don't know yeah I'm very
surprised all these people who think
they know people know so many things i
feel i as a i was engaging to meditation
i think the question is what do we what
do we living in this situation i think
it's not so easy to understand what is
happening to us and i find before trying
to know what will happen in the future
would be good to know what is happening
in the present and i found that is very
difficult to understand what is i think
now and as a philosopher I know that
philosophy is not about just make
commentary of actuality yeah on news but
philosophy take your time to see what
beyond what you see
and I think it is because we can make a
lot of vulgar pronouncements about
reality I'm working on that very
intensively I'm working to try to be at
the level of what is happening mm-hmm of
my meditation and in terms of philosophy
yeah but I think is more is more work
how you are you you you be at the level
of the situation are you you are you but
we miss a lot of knowledge that we were
going to have soon in the future but
able to understand more clearly but
I would say and maybe we can close
discussion on that I but at some time I
meditation helped me to be in kind of
insecurity and not be afraid of
insecurity you know by accepting
insecurity we can go beyond crisis the
field Anna arvind said in the crisis the
main important thing is to not repeating
to do what you already know but to
arrive to let go you preconception about
reality
mm-hmm Phyllis is really important
because what we know is not going to
work we have to create a new way and by
creating new ways not so easy you have
to accept uncertainty in this way
meditation is very helpful and I'm not
you know by simple I'm not and I gave a
lecture to people who direct important
[Music]
business and I'm not against talking to
people by business I'm not just
management and we took I took we had a
lot of exchange and some guide
meditation and it was a lot all of them
was to how to be in contact with what we
feel how to be in contact with
uncertainty and not being afraid of our
fear because this true this kind of fear
that week we found the strength to face
the situation and so that was actually
one of the one of the key point and the
second point is how to having some OOP
the time of intense suffering yeah could
we find hope and hope as a project for
future reality is we're not interesting
that to have planned because I think
like what Backson the French philosopher
of the beginning of the 20th century
Backson which said the future is not
existing in the present but the this
time is the creation of new
all the time so nobody we know the
pandemic will have this effect we don't
know what will happen and it's better to
be open to possibilities that exist that
to just try to put reality in our box
and so that that the second point is is
is is a ring this openness and OOP OOP
too is not to pry like that instead of
hope being you know trying to create
some kind of utopia a better world in
the future
hope is a kind of openness towards
reality that you know I like very much
to understand OOP
to go into account some people asked
count what will be the future that there
will be a good future or bad future and
concepts we can't know because no man
could have a relation to all or
everything that happens in a completely
objective way because we are part of
Freddy T we can't be outside of reality
so he said we nobody can know if the
future will be good or bad better or
worse but one thing as human beings we
all have the the the desire the
aspiration that the future will will be
better that some some more peaceful and
more loving one will will will be so a
fan oop is a way to lessen our own
aspiration that something will come from
this situation that will will be helpful
and this aspiration is not in the future
hope is in reality and by contacting
this Pope I feel more trust and
confidence and I have more confidence to
to see how I can help the world I am NOT
just when I have Autopia I'm waiting
that all the people do doing things and
get pissed off when things don't happen
the way I want when I go into this
understand
of all that I'm talking this aspiration
link in or energy in her life I that
overcome my depression that overcome my
discouragement I feel more trust more
confidence more strength that I can help
in my own way and I think that is more
important and the third third thing so
how to work with crisis and not afraid
of uncertainty to finding hope in in a
new way like aspiration and the third
way is we are free in a painful way in
one sense but we feel sometime in this
situation that we are not free that we
are completely trapped by the reality
and I think it's interesting to to to
what I learned from philosophy the 20th
century's philosophy is is we are put in
the world we have no choice we have to
desire throne in the world I ever
fainted Heidegger or I began some talk a
lot about freedom that we we have no
choice we we are free because we have no
choice to make something of the
situation and I find this ventures into
too
I'm not free because I can do whatever I
want I'm free because I have no other
choice to respond to the reality that's
great I am NOT free it is just what
thought could move as far how you say
movies for bad faith is bad faith but
you said that but yeah you can say bad
faith in English you can say that yeah
it's kind of this kind of is a lie
mmm-hmm it's a lie you you you try to
pretend that you you can't do you're not
free because of the situation but we
have free to do something to change of
you to and to make a choice and
that is why what meditation helped me to
to be in contact with not afraid of
uncertainty and finding way to overcome
crisis and what and what I said hope is
finding our inner inspiration and
knowing that whatever I do I have to
make choice and this choice is and
that's what Victor Frankel's discovered
right when he was in the concentration
camp yes and to freedom to make a choice
you have to make if you understand what
I'm saying about crisis about hope and
about freedom you see that this tree to
be in contact with them you have to
accept some kind of difficulties and
certainty mmm that is not so easy but
he's fantastic and that is why when I'm
trying to - what I found - don't be
afraid of your own and perfection brings
out the way you can have the strength to
change the situation your own situation
and the situation in the world hmm
beautiful thank you thank you very much
Fabrice that was really really great to
talk to you and a great conversation and
I I loved it thank you very much I hope
I hope that other people from the
English world can can benefit from from
your teachings and in your school and
and because I find myself agreeing with
everything you say I think I think it's
it's so true what you're saying so
thanks a lot thank you very much bye